Now, I don't usually like cartoons,
في العادة لا أحب الرسوم الكاريكاتورية،
I don't think many of them are funny,
لا أعتقد أن العديد منها مضحك،
I find them weird. But I love this cartoon from the New Yorker.
أجدها غريبة. ولكني أحب هذا الكرتون من مجلة نيويوركر.
(Text: Never, ever think outside the box.) (Laughter)
(النص: لا تفكر بصورة مختلفة .) (ضحك)
So, the guy is telling the cat,
اذن، يقول الرجل للقط،
don't you dare think outside the box.
إياك أن تجرؤ على التفكير خارج الصندوق
Well, I'm afraid I used to be the cat.
حسنا، أخشى أنني انا هذا القط
I always wanted to be outside the box.
أردت دائماً أن أفكر بصورة مختلفة.
And it's partly because I came to this field
ويرجع ذلك جزئياً إلى أنني دخلت هذا المجال
from a different background, chemist and a bacterial geneticist.
من خلفية مختلفة، عالمة كيمياء ووراثة بكتيرية
So, what people were saying to me
لذا، ما كان الناس يقولونه لي
about the cause of cancer, sources of cancer,
حول سبب السرطان، ومصادره
or, for that matter, why you are who you are,
أو، لتلك المسألة، لماذا أنت من أنت،
didn't make sense.
لم يكن له معنى.
So, let me quickly try and tell you why I thought that
لذا، اسمحوا لي أن أحاول أخباركم بسرعة لماذا اعتقدت ذلك
and how I went about it.
وكيف مضيت في ذلك الطريق.
So, to begin with, however,
اذن، بادئ ذي بدء،
I have to give you a very, very quick lesson
لا بد لي أن أعطيكم درسًا سريعًا جدًا
in developmental biology,
في علم الأحياء التطوري،
with apologies to those of you who know some biology.
ومع الاعتذار لأولئك الذين يعرفون بعض الأحياء.
So, when your mom and dad met,
لذا، عندما اجتمع أمي وأبي،
there is a fertilized egg,
تكونت بويضة مخصبة،
that round thing with that little blip.
ذلك الشيء المستدير الذي تخرج منه بقعة.
It grows and then it grows,
تكبر الخلايا وتكبر،
and then it makes this handsome man.
وبعدها تصنع هذا الرجل الوسيم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, this guy, with all the cells in his body,
إذًا، هذا الرجل، مع كل هذه الخلايا في جسده،
all have the same genetic information.
تحمل جميعها نفس المعلومات الوراثية.
So how did his nose become his nose, his elbow his elbow,
وكيف أصبح أنفه هو أنفه، ومرفقه هو مرفقه،
and why doesn't he get up one morning
لماذا لا يستيقظ في يوم من الأيام
and have his nose turn into his foot?
ويجد أنفه قد تحول إلى قدمه؟
It could. It has the genetic information.
قد يحدث. كلاهما يحملان المعلومات الوراثية.
You all remember, dolly,
جميعكم تتذكرون النعجة دولي،
it came from a single mammary cell.
جاءت من خلية ثديية واحدة.
So, why doesn't it do it?
إذًا لماذا لا يحدث هذا؟
So, have a guess of how many cells he has in his body.
هل يمكنكم تخمين عدد الخلايا في جسمه؟
Somewhere between 10 trillion to 70 trillion cells in his body.
ما بين ١٠ تريليون و٧٠ تريليون خلية في جسده.
Trillion!
تريليون!
Now, how did these cells, all with the same genetic material,
الآن، كيف تمكنت هذه الخلايا، التي تحمل نفس المعلومات الوراثية،
make all those tissues?
من تكوين هذه الأنسجة المختلفة؟
And so, the question I raised before
إذًا السؤال الذي سألته سابقاً
becomes even more interesting if you thought about
يصبح مثيراَ أكثر إذا تأملنا
the enormity of this in every one of your bodies.
ضخامة العدد في كل واحد من أجسامنا.
Now, the dominant cancer theory would say
تقول نظرية السرطان السائدة
that there is a single oncogene
أن هناك جين سرطاني واحد
in a single cancer cell, and it would make you
في خلية سرطانية واحدة، وهذا سيجعلك
a cancer victim.
من ضحايا السرطان.
Well, this did not make sense to me.
هذا لم يكن منطقياً لي.
Do you even know how a trillion looks?
هل تعرفون كيف يبدو التريلون؟
Now, let's look at it.
دعونا ننظر إليه
There it comes, these zeroes after zeroes after zeroes.
هذا هو، أصفار بعد أصفار بعد أصفار.
Now, if .0001 of these cells got mutated,
إذا تحور ٠.٠٠١ من هذه الخلايا
and .00001 got cancer, you will be a lump of cancer.
وإذا أصيبت ٠.٠٠٠٠١ بالسرطان، ستصبح أنت كتلة سرطانية.
You will have cancer all over you. And you're not.
سيغطي السرطان جسمك. لكن هذا لم يحدث.
Why not?
لماذا لا؟
So, I decided over the years,
لذا، قررت على مر السنين،
because of a series of experiments
بسبب سلسلة من التجارب
that this is because of context and architecture.
أنه بسبب التركيب والهندسة.
And let me quickly tell you
واسمحوا لي أن أقول لكم بسرعة
some crucial experiment that was able to actually show this.
بعض التجارب الحاسمة التي تمكنت من إظهار هذا.
To begin with, I came to work with this virus
في البداية، كنت أعمل مع هذا الفايروس.
that causes that ugly tumor in the chicken.
الذي يسبب هذا الورم القبيح في الدجاجة.
Rous discovered this in 1911.
راوس اكتشفه في ١٩١١.
It was the first cancer virus discovered,
كان أول فايروس سرطاني يتم اكتشافه.
and when I call it "oncogene," meaning "cancer gene."
وعندما أطلق عليه اسم "الجين الورمي" فهذا معناه "الجين السرطاني".
So, he made a filtrate, he took this filter
قام راوس بالترشيح
which was the liquid after he passed the tumor through a filter,
أخذ السائل الذي حصل عليه بعد ترشيح الورم،
and he injected it to another chicken, and he got another tumor.
وحقنه في دجاجة أخرى، فحصل على ورم آخر.
So, scientists were very excited,
شعر العلماء بالإثارة
and they said, a single oncogene can do it.
وقالوا أن جين سرطاني واحد يستطيع عمل هذا.
All you need is a single oncogene.
كل ما تحتاجه هو جين مسرطن واحد.
So, they put the cells in cultures, chicken cells,
لذا قاموا بوضع الخلايا في خلايا الدجاج
dumped the virus on it,
وألقوا بالفيروس فيها،
and it would pile up,
وتركوها تتراكم،
and they would say, this is malignant and this is normal.
وكانوا سيقولون هذا خبيت وهذا طبيعي.
And again this didn't make sense to me.
ومرة أخرى هذا لم يكن منطقي بالنسبة لي.
So for various reasons, we took this oncogene,
لذا لعدة أسباب ، قمنا بأخذ الجين الورمي
attached it to a blue marker,
وقمنا بتعليمه باللون الأزرق،
and we injected it into the embryos.
وقمنا بحقنه في الأجنة
Now look at that. There is that beautiful feather in the embryo.
الآن انظروا إلى هذا، انظروا إلى هذا الريش الجميل في الأجنة.
Every one of those blue cells are a cancer gene
كل واحدة من هذه الخلايا الزرقاء هي جين سرطاني
inside a cancer cell, and they're part of the feather.
بداخل خلية سرطاينة، وهي جزء من الريش
So, when we dissociated the feather and put it in a dish,
لذا عندما فصلنا الريش ووضعناه في طبق،
we got a mass of blue cells.
حصلنا على كمية من الخلايا الزرقاء
So, in the chicken you get a tumor,
لذا، في الدجاج حصلنا على ورم،
in the embryo you don't,
وفي الريش لا،
you dissociate, you put it in a dish, you get another tumor.
تقوم بالفصل، تضعه في صحن، تحصل على ورم آخر
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني هذا؟
That means that microenvironment
هذا يعني أن هذه البيئة متناهية الصغر
and the context which surrounds those cells
والسياق الذي يحيط هذه الخلايا
actually are telling the cancer gene and the cancer cell what to do.
في الحقيقة يخبر الخلية السرطانية والسرطان ماذا يفعلان
Now, let's take a normal example.
الآن ، دعونا نأخذ مثالا طبيعيا.
The normal example, let's take the human mammary gland.
المثال الطبيعي ، دعنا نأخذ الغدة الثديية البشرية
I work on breast cancer.
أنا أعمل على سرطان الثدي
So, here is a lovely human breast.
لذا، هذا صدر بشري جميل.
And many of you know how it looks,
والكثير منكم يعرفون كيف يبدو شكله،
except that inside that breast, there are all these
ما عدا أن بداخل هذا الصدر ، هناك كل هذه الأشياء
pretty, developing, tree-like structures.
الجميلة ، النامية، التي تبدوا شبيهة بتركيب الشجرة
So, we decided that what we like to do
لذا ، قررنا ماذا نود أن نفعل
is take just a bit of that mammary gland,
ونأخذ جزء بسيط من الغدة الثديية،
which is called an "acinus,"
والتي يطلق عليها "حبة" ،
where there are all these little things inside the breast
حيث توجد كل هذه الأشياء الصغيرة بداخل الصدر
where the milk goes, and the end of the nipple
حيث يذهب الحليب ، و في نهاية الحلمة
comes through that little tube when the baby sucks.
يمر الأنبوب الصغير الذي يرضعه الطفل.
And we said, wonderful! Look at this pretty structure.
ونحن نقول ، جميل! انظروا إلى هذا التشكيل الجميل
We want to make this a structure, and ask the question,
نحن نريد أن نقوم بعمل هذا التركيب ، ونسأل هذا السؤال،
how do the cells do that?
كيف تقوم هذه الخلايا بعمل هذا؟
So, we took the red cells --
لذا، قمنا بأخذ الخلايا الحمراء --
you see the red cells are surrounded by blue,
انتم ترون الخلايا الحمراء محاطة بالخلايا الزرقاء،
other cells that squeeze them, and behind it
الخلايا الأخرى تقوم بعصرها ، ومن خلفها
is material that people thought was mainly inert,
هي المادة التي كان يظنها الناس خاملة،
and it was just having a structure to keep the shape,
وهي تتخذ شكلا لتقوم بحفظ الشكل،
and so we first photographed it
لذا قمنا في البداية بتصويرها
with the electron microscope years and years ago,
بالمنظار الالكتروني قبل سنوات عديدة،
and you see this cell is actually quite pretty.
وكما ترون هذه الخلية شكلها جميل
It has a bottom, it has a top,
لها قاع وقمة،
it is secreting gobs and gobs of milk,
هي تقوم بإفراز كتل وكتل من الحليب ،
because it just came from an early pregnant mouse.
لأنها جاءت من أنثى فأر حامل في مراحل مبكرة،
You take these cells, you put them in a dish,
تقوم بأخذ هذه الخلايا ، وتقوم بوضعها في صحن،
and within three days, they look like that.
وفي خلال ثلاثة أيام، يبدو شكلها هكذا.
They completely forget.
تنسى تماماً .
So you take them out, you put them in a dish,
إذا أنت تقوم بأخذها، تضعها في صحن،
they don't make milk. They completely forget.
ومن ثم تنسى صناعة الحليب, هي تنسى كل شيء تماما.
For example, here is a lovely yellow droplet of milk
على سبيل المثال، هنا قطرات صفراء جميلة من الحليب
on the left, there is nothing on the right.
في اليسار, وفي اليمين لا يوجد شيء.
Look at the nuclei. The nuclei in the cell on the left
انظروا إلى النواة, نواة الخلية الموجودة على اليسار
is in the animal, the one on the right is in a dish.
موجودة في الحيوان. والتي على اليمين موجودة في الصحن
They are completely different from each other.
هما مختلفتان تماما عن بعضهما.
So, what does this tell you?
إذاً ، ماذا يخبرنا ذلك؟
This tells you that here also, context overrides.
هنا أيضاً هذا يخبرنا ، أن السياق يتبدل.
In different contexts, cells do different things.
في سياق مختلف، الخلايا تفعل أشياء مختلفة.
But how does context signal?
لكن كيف يقوم السياق بإرسال الإشارات؟
So, Einstein said that
إذا، يقول انشتاين
"For an idea that does not first seem insane, there is no hope."
"ليس هناك أمل ، لفكرة لا تبدو مجنونة لأول وهلة"
So, you can imagine the amount of skepticism
لذا يمكنك تخيل مقدار الشك
I received -- couldn't get money,
الذي تلقيته -- لا يمكنني الحصول على مال،
couldn't do a whole lot of other things,
لا يمكنني عمل الكثير من الأشياء،
but I'm so glad it all worked out.
لكنني فخورة بأن كل الأشياء قد عملت.
So, we made a section of the mammary gland of the mouse,
لذا، قمنا بعمل مقطع من الغدة الثديية للفأر،
and all those lovely acini are there,
وكل العنيبات الجميلة كانت موجودة،
every one of those with the red around them are an acinus,
كل واحدو من ذوات اللون الأحمر هي حبة،
and we said okay, we are going to try and make this,
ونحن نقول حسنا، نحن سنقوم بالمحاولة وعمل ذلك،
and I said, maybe that red stuff
وأنا أقول ، ربما الحمراوات
around the acinus that people think there's just a structural scaffold,
الموجودة حول العنيبات والتي يعتقد الناس أنها مجرد تشكيل للسقالة،
maybe it has information,
ربما لديها المعلومات،
maybe it tells the cells what to do, maybe it tells the nucleus what to do.
ربما تقوم بإخبار الخلايا ماذا تفعل, ربما تخبر النواة ماذا تفعل.
So I said, extracellular matrix, which is this stuff
لذا انا قلت ، مصفوفة خارج الخلايا، والتي هي هذه الأشياء
called ECM, signals and actually tells the cells what to do.
نطلق عليها اسم 'ECM" ، ترسل إشارات وتخبر الخلايا ماذا تفعل في الحقيقة
So, we decided to make things that would look like that.
لذا ، قررنا أن نقوم بعمل أشياء تبدو كهذه.
We found some gooey material
وجدنا بعض المواد اللزجة
that had the right extracellular matrix in it,
والتي لديها نفس المصفوفة بداخلها
we put the cells in it, and lo and behold,
وضعنا الخلايا بداخلها ، وانظروا ماذا وجدنا
in about four days, they got reorganized
في حوالي أربعة أيام ،وتم إعادة تنظيمها
and on the right, is what we can make in culture.
وعلى اليمين، هو ما يمكن أن نقوم بعمله بالاستنبات
On the left is what's inside the animal, we call it in vivo,
وفي اليسار هو ما يوجد بداخل الحيوان، نحن نقول عنها في الحياة،
and the one in culture was full of milk,
والتي في الاستنبات كانت مليئة بالحليب،
the lovely red there is full of milk.
الحمراء الجميلة كانت مليئة بالحليب.
So, we Got Milk, for the American audience.
إذاُ ، نحن لدينا حليب ، من أجل الحضور الأمريكي.
All right. And here is this beautiful human cell,
حسناً ، وهنا هذه الخلية البشرية الجميلة،
and you can imagine that here also, context goes.
ويمكنك التخيل أن السياق يذهب
So, what do we do now?
لذا ، ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل؟
I made a radical hypothesis.
لقد قمت بعمل فرضية متطرفة.
I said, if it's true that architecture is dominant,
لقد قلت ، إذا كان صحيحا أن الهندسة هي المهيمنة ،
architecture restored to a cancer cell
البنية هي التي تعيد الخلية السرطانية
should make the cancer cell think it's normal.
يجب أن تعيد الخلية السرطانية إلى طبيعتها .
Could this be done?
هل من الممكن حدوث هذا؟
So, we tried it.
لذا، قمنا بتجربة ذلك.
In order to do that, however,
من أجل القيام بذلك،
we needed to have a method of distinguishing normal from malignant,
يجب أن نجد طريقة للتمييز بين الخلايا الطبيعية و الخبيثة،
and on the left is the single normal cell,
هذه خلية سليمة على اليسار ،
human breast, put in three-dimensional gooey gel
من صدر بشري، تم وضعها في هلام لزج ثلاثي الأبعاد
that has extracellular matrix, it makes all these beautiful structures.
لديها مصفوفة خارج الخلية، تقوم بعمل كل هذه التركيبات الجميلة
On the right, you see it looks very ugly,
على اليمين ، كما ترى يبدو شكلها قبيحاً،
the cells continue to grow,
ما زالت الخلية تنمو،
the normal ones stop.
الخلية السليمة توقفت عن النمو.
And you see here in higher magnification
وانت ترى في التكبير الأعلى
the normal acinus and the ugly tumor.
العنبية السليمة و الورم القبيح.
So we said, what is on the surface of these ugly tumors?
لذا قلنا ، ماذا يوجد على سطح هذا الورم القبيح؟
Could we calm them down --
هل يمكننا أن نهدئها --
they were signaling like crazy and they have pathways all messed up --
هم يقومون بإرسال إشارات كالمجانين ولديهم مسارات فاسدة --
and make them to the level of the normal?
ونقوم بجعلها طبيعية إلى درجة ما؟
Well, it was wonderful. Boggles my mind.
حسنا. كان هذا جميلاً. كان يحير عقلي.
This is what we got.
هذا ما حصلنا عليه.
We can revert the malignant phenotype.
يمكننا الرجوع إلى النمط السليم للخبيثة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And in order to show you that the malignant phenotype
ومن أجل جعلكم ترون أن النمط الظاهري للخلية الخبيثة
I didn't just choose one,
لم يقم فقط باختيار واحدة
here are little movies, sort of fuzzy,
هناك أفلام صغيرة ، نوع من الغموض
but you see that on the left are the malignant cells,
لكن كما ترون على اليسار هي الخلايا الخبيثة
all of them are malignant,
جميعها خبيثة
we add one single inhibitor in the beginning,
نحن قمنا بإضافة مثبط واحد فقط في البداية
and look what happens, they all look like that.
وانظروا ماذا حدث، كلها صارت بهذا الشكل.
We inject them into the mouse, the ones on the right,
قمنا بحقنها في الفأر, التي على اليمين
and none of them would make tumors.
ولم تقم ولا واحدة منها بعمل أورام.
We inject the other ones in the mouse, 100 percent tumors.
قمان بحقن البقية في الفأر، أورام بنسبة 100%
So, it's a new way of thinking about cancer,
إذاً ، هذه طريقة جديدة للتفكير حول السرطان،
it's a hopeful way of thinking about cancer.
إنها طريقة مليئة بالأمل للتفكير بالسرطان.
We should be able to be dealing with these things at this level,
يجب ان نكون قادرين على التعامل مع أشياء بهذا المستوى
and these conclusions say that growth and malignant behavior
وهذه الخاتمة تقول أن النمو والسلوك الخبيثان
is regulated at the level of tissue organization
يتم تنظيمها على مستوى الأنسجة
and that the tissue organization is dependent
وأن ورم الأنسجة يعتمد
on the extracellular matrix and the microenvironment.
على المصفوفة خارج الخلية والبيئة المحيطة بها
All right, thus form and function interact dynamically and reciprocally.
حسنا ، الشكل والوظيفة تتفاعل ديناميكيا و تتبادل
And here is another five seconds of repose,
وهذه خمس ثوان أخرى من الراحة
is my mantra. Form and function.
هو شعاري, الشكل والوظيفة.
And of course, we now ask, where do we go now?
وبالطبع ، نحن نسأل الآن, إلى أين نحن ذاهبون؟
We'd like to take this kind of thinking into the clinic.
يجب أن نأخذ هذا النوع من التفكير إلى العيادة
But before we do that, I'd like you to think
لكن قبل أن نفعل هذا ، يجب أن نفكر
that at any given time when you're sitting there,
إنه في أي وقت بينما نحن جالسون هناك
in your 70 trillion cells,
في السبعين تريليون خلية
the extracellular matrix signaling to your nucleus,
المصفوفة المحيطة ترسل إشارات إلى نواياك
the nucleus is signaling to your extracellular matrix
وهي تقوم بإرسال إشارات للمصفوفة
and this is how your balance is kept and restored.
وهكذا يتم حفظ التوازن واستعادته.
We have made a lot of discoveries,
قمنا بالعديد من الاكتشافات،
we have shown that extracellular matrix talks to chromatin.
قمنا بعرض حوار المصفوفات إلى الكروماتين
We have shown that there's little pieces of DNA
لقد عرفنا أن هناك قطع صغيرة من الحامض النووي
on the specific genes of the mammary gland
في جينات معينة من الغدة الثديية
that actually respond to extracellular matrix.
تقوم بالاستجابة إلى المصفوفة.
It has taken many years, but it has been very rewarding.
لقد استغرق هذه عدة سنوات ، لكن هذا كان مجزيا جداً.
And before I get to the next slide, I have to tell you
وقبل أن إذهب إلى الشريحة التالية ، أود إخباركم
that there are so many additional discoveries to be made.
هنالك العديد من الأشياء التي نحن بحاجة إلى اكتشافها.
There is so much mystery we don't know.
هنالك لغز لا نعرفه.
And I always say to the students and post-docs I lecture to,
ودائما ما أقول للطبية الذين أقوم بتدريسهم
don't be arrogant, because arrogance kills curiosity.
لا تكن متغطرساً ، فالتغطرس يقتل الفضول.
Curiosity and passion.
الفضول والعاطفة.
You need to always think, what else needs to be discovered?
انت بحاجة دائمة إلى التفكير. ما الذي يجب ان تقوم باكتشافه أيضاً؟
And maybe my discovery needs to be added to
وربما أنا بحاجة إلى إضافة المزيد إلى اكتشافي
or maybe it needs to be changed.
أو ربما بحاجة إلى التغيير.
So, we have now made an amazing discovery,
لذا ، قمنا بعمل اكتشاف مذهل،
a post-doc in the lab who is a physicist asked me,
أحد طلبة الدكتوراة والذي هو فيزيائي سألني
what do the cells do when you put them in?
ما الذي تقوم بعمله الخلية عندما نقوم بوضعها في الداخل؟
What do they do in the beginning when they do?
ماذا تفعل في البداية عندما تعمل؟
I said, I don't know, we couldn't look at them.
قلت له ، لا لأعلم، لا يمكننا النظر إليهم.
We didn't have high images in the old days.
لم يكن لدينا صور واضحة في الأيام الخوالي.
So she, being an imager and a physicist,
حسنا ، هي مصورة وفيزيائية،
did this incredible thing.
قامت بعمل هذا الشيء الرائع.
This is a single human breast cell in three dimensions.
هذه خلية من صدر بشري في ثلاثة أبعاد.
Look at it. It's constantly doing this.
انظروا إليها ، إنها تقوم بعمل هذا دائما.
Has a coherent movement.
تقوم بعمل هذه الحركة المتناسقة.
You put the cancer cells there, and they do go all over,
تقوم بوضع الخلايا السرطانية هناك ، ومن ثم تنتشر في كل مكان،
they do this. They don't do this.
هي تقوم بعمل ذلك. لا تقوم بعمل ذلك.
And when we revert the cancer cell, it again does this.
ثم نقوم بإعادة الخلية السرطانية، ومن ثم تقوم بعمل ذلك مرة أخرى
Absolutely boggles my mind.
تحير ذهني تماماً.
So the cell acts like an embryo. What an exciting thing.
وبالتالي فإن الخلايا تعمل مثل الجنين. يا له من شيء مثير.
So I'd like to finish with a poem.
أود أن أنهي بمقطع من الشعر.
Well I used to love English literature,
في الحقيقة أنا أحب الأدب الانجليزي،
and I debated in college, which one should I do?
وكنت أقوم بالمناظرة في الكلية، ما الذي يجب أن أقوم بعمله؟
And unfortunately or fortunately, chemistry won.
ولسوء الحظ أو لحسن الحظ ، انتصرت الكيمياء.
But here is a poem from Yeats. I'll just read you the last two lines.
لكن هناك مقطع شعري لييتس. سأقوم بقراءة آخر سطرين فقط.
It's called "Among the School Children."
اسمها "بين أطفال المدارس".
"O body swayed to music / O brightening glance /
"أوه يتمايل الجسم مع الموسيقى \ أوه اللمحة تزداد إضاءة\
How [can we know] the dancer from the dance?"
كيف "نستطيع أن نعرف" الراقص من الرقصة؟
And here is Merce Cunningham,
وهاهو الراقص ميرسي كوننقهام
I was fortunate to dance with him when I was younger,
كنت محظوظاً لأنني رقصت معه عندما كنت أصغر ،
and here he is a dancer,
وهاهو الراقص،
and while he is dancing, he is both the dancer and the dance.
وبينما هو يرقص. كان الاثنان معا الراقص والرقصة.
The minute he stops, we have neither.
في اللحظة التي توقف فيها ، فقدنا الاثنين معا.
So it's like form and function.
إذا هي كالشكل والوظيفة.
Now, I'd like to show you a current picture of my group.
الآن ، اود أن أريكم صورة حديثة لمجموعتي.
I have been fortunate to have had these magnificant
أنا محظوظة لأنني املك هولاء الطلبة
students and post-docs who have taught me so much,
المميزين وطلبة الدكتوراة الذين قاموا بتعليمي الكثير،
and I have had many of these groups come and go.
ولدي الكثير من هذه المجموعات التي تأتي وتذهب.
They are the future and I try to make them not be afraid
هم المستقبل. وأنا احاول أن اجعلهم لا يخافون
of being the cat and being told,
أن يكونوا هذا القط وان يقال لهم
don't think outside the box.
لا تفكروا خارج الصندوق.
And I'd like to leave you with this thought.
وأود أن أترككم مع هذا التفكير.
On the left is water coming through the shore,
على اليسار ماء يأتي عبر الشاطئ
taken from a NASA satellite.
تم التقاطها من قمر لوكالة ناسا
On the right, there is a coral.
وعلى اليمين ، هذه شعب مرجانية
Now if you take the mammary gland and spread it
الآن إذا قمت بأخذ غدة ثديية وقمت بنشرها
and take the fat away, on a dish it looks like that.
وقمت بأخذ الدسم خارجا ووضعها في صحن ستبدو هكذا.
Do they look the same? Do they have the same patterns?
هل تبدو متشابهة؟ هل لديها نفس النمط؟
Why is it that nature keeps doing that over and over again?
لماذا تقوم الطبيعة بعمل هذا مرارا وتكرارا؟
And I'd like to submit to you
وأود أن أقدم إليكم هذا
that we have sequenced the human genome,
لقد قمنا بعمل تسلسل للجين البشري،
we know everything about the sequence of the gene,
نحن نعرف أي شيء عن التسلسل الجيني
the language of the gene, the alphabet of the gene,
لغة الجينات. أبجدية الجيانت
But we know nothing, but nothing,
لكن نحن لا نعلم شيئا,
about the language and alphabet of form.
عن لغة وأبجدية الشكل
So, it's a wonderful new horizon,
لذا هذا أفق جديد جميل
it's a wonderful thing to discover for the young
هي شيء جميل للاكتشاف للشباب
and the passionate old, and that's me.
وكبيرة السن الشغوفة، والتي هي أنا .
So go to it!
لذا انطلقوا إليها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)